Guide to the Records of the Edwin Berry Burgum Academic Freedom Case RG.19.1
New York University Archives
- Series IV. Office of the Dean, Washington Square College, 1941-2008; 1.75 Linear Feet in one manuscript box, one half manuscript box, and one record carton
  Series IV consists of a variety of materials from Dean Thomas Pollock. While some of the material consists of copies and duplicates of records from other series, such as Dean Pollock's statement before the Senate Faculty Committee, Senate Faculty Committee reports, and Burgum's correspondence with the administration among others, much of the material is unique. This includes statements and reports from Rutgers and Harvard Universities concerning academic freedom and tenure cases; correspondence between Dean Pollock and Allan Riggs, Pollock's legal counsel from New York University's School of Law; and a transcript of Burgum's testimony in 1941 before the Rapp-Coudert Committee, an investigation undertaken by the New York State Senate into the assumed existence of teachers of communist affiliation within New York City's municipal school system.
  - Transcript of Burgum's testimony before Rapp-Coudert Committee, Apr 1941 (Box 6, Folder 19)
  - Aurther Lovejoy re: Academic Freedom vs. Communism, 1949-1953 (Box 6, Folder 20)
  - Letter to Dr. M. Schlauch, Jul 1951 (Box 6, Folder 21)
  - Statement by Dr. Riggs, Jan 1952 (Box 6, Folder 22)
  - Testimony of Burgum before McCarran Committee, Oct 1952 (Box 6, Folder 23)
  - List of Burgum's organizational affiliations, Nov 1952 (Box 6, Folder 24)
  - Burgum's corr. with administration, Mar 1942, Jun 1952-Feb 1953, Jun 1952-Feb 1953 (Box 6, Folder 25)
  - Henry Heald-Howard Jones corr., Dec 1952 (Box 6, Folder 26)
  - Copy of Burgum speech and corr., Nov 1952-Jun 1953 (Box 6, Folder 27)
  - Pollock-Riggs corr. re: Burgum case, ca.Nov 1952-Apr 1953, Apr 1955, Apr 1955 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Rutger's University: Heimlich-Finley cases, Sep 1952-Jan 1953 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Handbills re: Burgum and academic freedom, Oct 1952-May 1953 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Heald-Burgum corr. with Heald speech re: Burgum case, Oct 1952-Jan 1953 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Harvard University: Academic freedom and tenure case, Jan 1953-May 1953 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Dean Pollock's statement before Faculty Committee, Feb 1953 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Chronology and statement re: Burgum case, Oct 1953-Apr 1953 (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Senate Committee report, Apr 1953 (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Rigg's statement before the Senate Council, Apr 1953 (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - Inventory re: Burgum material, Jan 1957 (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - Committee on Discipline, 1950-1958 (Box 7, Folder 11)
  - Special Committee on Faculty Responsibility, 1952-1953 (Box 7, Folder 12)
  - Newspaper clippings, 1953 (Box 7, Folder 13)
  - Heald-Pollack correspondence, 1952 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Dean Pollack's statement, 1953 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Council Actions, 1952-1953 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Report of Committee A, 1959-1960 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - NYU Statement, 1953 (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Minutes of NYU Council, 1952 (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - AAUP, "Academic Freedom and Tenure in the Quest for Security," CONFIDENTIAL DRAFT, 1956 (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - NYU Investigating Committee Report - CONFIDENTIAL, 1957 (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - Senate Faculty Committee Hearings, 1953 (Box 8, Folder 9)
  - NYU Council meeting, 1953-04-27 (Box 8, Folder 10-11)
  - Square Bulletin, 1952-1954 (Box 8, Folder 12-13)
  - FBI files, 2008 (Box 8, Folder 14-15)
  - Dinner invitation, [1950] (Box 8, Folder 16)
  - Court publications, 1951-1952 (Box 8, Folder 17)
  - Committee for Reinstatement: Academic Freedom and New York University, 1954 (Box 8, Folder 18)
  - Publications on academic freedom and tenure, 1953-1958 (Box 8, Folder 19)
  - AAUP Bulletin, 1949, 1952 (Box 8, Folder 20)
  - Edwin Berry Burgum published articles, 1943-1944 (Box 8, Folder 21)
  - Edwin Berry Burgum, The Novel and the World's Dilemma, 1953 (Box 8, Folder 22)
  - Bound volume: Report of the Senate Faculty Committee and of University Council Meeting on Charges against Prof. E. B. Burgum, 1953 (Box 8)
  - Bound volumes: Hearings on Charges Against Prof. E. B. Burgum, v. 1 and 2, 1953 (Box 8)